import { Question } from "@/types/Question";

export const questionsByWeek: { [week: string]: Question[] } = {
	week1: [
		{
			question: "Match List-I (Air pollution events/accidents) with List-II (Year) and select the correct answer using the codes given below: List I (Air pollution events/accidents) List II (Year) A. Donora, Pennsylvania 1. 1984 B. Los Angeles smog 2. 1948 C. Bhopal Gas Tragedy 3. 1954 D. Vapour Cloud Explosion 4. 2009",
			options: [
				"A-2, B-3, C-1, D-4",
				"A-4, B-1, C-3, D-2",
				"A-4, B-3, C-2, D-4",
				"A-1, B-2, C-3, D-1",
			],
			answer: "A-2, B-3, C-1, D-4",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following fuels was banned by King Edward-I of England in 1307?",
			options: [
				"Wood",
				"Coal",
				"Both coal and wood",
				"Fossil fuel",
			],
			answer: "Coal",
		},
		{
			question: "The lithosphere includes: 1. Crust 2. Uppermost mantle 3. Water over the earth 4. Water beneath the earth Select the correct combination:",
			options: [
				"1, 2, 3",
				"2, 3",
				"1, 2",
				"1, 4",
			],
			answer: "1, 2",
		},
		{
			question: "How can chemical transformation affect air pollutants?",
			options: [
				"By neutralizing them",
				"By forming secondary pollutants",
				"By making them harmless",
				"By increasing their density",
			],
			answer: "By forming secondary pollutants",
		},
		{
			question: "What are Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons (PAHs) primarily found in?",
			options: [
				"Water and air",
				"Coal and tar sediments",
				"Vegetation",
				"Natural gas",
			],
			answer: "Coal and tar sediments",
		},
		{
			question: "Forest fires contribute to the presence of Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons (PAHs) in the environment because they involve:",
			options: [
				"Incomplete combustion of organic matter",
				"Complete combustion of trees",
				"Chemical reactions in the soil",
				"Evaporation of water vapor",
			],
			answer: "Incomplete combustion of organic matter",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following is the short-term effects of dioxin on humans?",
			options: [
				"vomiting",
				"coughing",
				"dark spots and lesions on the skin",
				"throat irritation",
			],
			answer: "dark spots and lesions on the skin",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following pollutants is NOT mentioned as causing organ toxicity in animals?",
			options: [
				"Carbon monoxide (CO)",
				"Nitrous oxide (N₂O)",
				"Ammonia (NH₃)",
				"Mercury",
			],
			answer: "Nitrous oxide (N₂O)",
		},
		{
			question: "What is a major stressor to biodiversity caused by air pollution?",
			options: [
				"Excess deposition of airborne nitrogen in the form of ammonia",
				"Carbon dioxide emissions",
				"Ozone layer depletion",
				"Acid rain",
			],
			answer: "Excess deposition of airborne nitrogen in the form of ammonia",
		},
		{
			question: "As a preservative coating on the building surface, materials used like acrylic copolymers and siloxanes because of their ___________film forming properties.",
			options: [
				"Good cohesion",
				"Good adhesion",
				"Weak cohesion",
				"Weak adhesion",
			],
			answer: "Good adhesion",
		},
	],
	week2: [
		{
			question: "Why is albedo a significant concern in climatology?",
			options: [
				"It influences global wind patterns",
				"It directly increases greenhouse gas emissions",
				"It reduces atmospheric oxygen levels",
				"A decrease in albedo increases heat absorption, causing ice to melt",
			],
			answer: "A decrease in albedo increases heat absorption, causing ice to melt",
		},
		{
			question: "What happens when soot enters the atmosphere?",
			options: [
				"It reflects sunlight, cooling the air",
				"It absorbs sunlight and generates heat, warming the air",
				"It mixes with clouds to form rain",
				"It increases the albedo of the Earth's surface",
			],
			answer: "It absorbs sunlight and generates heat, warming the air",
		},
		{
			question: "How does soot affect snow and ice after being deposited?",
			options: [
				"It reduces their albedo, absorbing more sunlight",
				"It increases their albedo, reflecting more sunlight",
				"It has no significant impact on snow and ice",
				"It accelerates the formation of glaciers",
			],
			answer: "It reduces their albedo, absorbing more sunlight",
		},
		{
			question: "In water bodies, which gas can be depleted by eutrophication?",
			options: [
				"CO2",
				"SO2",
				"O2",
				"CO",
			],
			answer: "O2",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following is NOT a type of marine aerosol?",
			options: [
				"Sea salt",
				"Sulfate aerosol",
				"Mineral dust",
				"Methane gas",
			],
			answer: "Methane gas",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the approximate size of jet drops compared to their precursor bubble diameter?",
			options: [
				"50%",
				"25%",
				"10%",
				"5%",
			],
			answer: "10%",
		},
		{
			question: "Select the incorrect pair of given particulate matter.",
			options: [
				"Dust 1 to 200 μm",
				"Smoke 0.01 to 1 μm",
				"Fumes 0.1 to 1 μm",
				"Mist greater than 1 μm",
			],
			answer: "Mist greater than 1 μm",
		},
		{
			question: "____________ is one of the processes of movement of gases and liquids (fluids) to transfer heat between regions of different temperatures.",
			options: [
				"Advection",
				"Convection",
				"Diffusion",
				"Dispersion",
			],
			answer: "Convection",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the primary role of the hydroxyl radical (OH) in the troposphere?",
			options: [
				"Control the atmospheric lifetime of gases",
				"Absorb UV radiation",
				"Cause acid rain",
				"Act as a greenhouse gas",
			],
			answer: "Control the atmospheric lifetime of gases",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following phenomena is responsible for transferring the heat energy from the tropics to the poles to create atmospheric circulation?",
			options: [
				"Conduction",
				"Convection",
				"Advection",
				"Pyrolysis",
			],
			answer: "Advection",
		},
	],
	week3: [
		{
			question: "Which of the following factors is NOT associated with the plume properties? A. Exit velocity B. Turbulence C. Atmospheric Stability D. Wind Speed Select the correct option:",
			options: [
				"A, & B",
				"A, C, D",
				"B, C, D",
				"A, B, C, D",
			],
			answer: "A, & B",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following plume types exists under the neutral lapse rate when wind speed is greater than 32 km per hour?",
			options: [
				"Looping",
				"Fanning",
				"Coning",
				"Lofting",
			],
			answer: "Coning",
		},
		{
			question: "During which time is the height of the Mixed Layer typically the highest?",
			options: [
				"Early morning in winter",
				"Late afternoon in summer",
				"Late evening in spring",
				"Midnight during fall",
			],
			answer: "Late afternoon in summer",
		},
		{
			question: "What causes turbulence in the Mixed Layer?",
			options: [
				"Gravitational waves",
				"Decreasing atmospheric pressure",
				"Ozone formation in the stratosphere",
				"Solar heating and strong winds",
			],
			answer: "Solar heating and strong winds",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following is a component of the Atmospheric Boundary Layer?",
			options: [
				"Tropospheric layer",
				"Stratospheric layer",
				"Stable boundary layer",
				"Thermospheric layer",
			],
			answer: "Stable boundary layer",
		},
		{
			question: "What is one of the primary objectives of (National Air Quality Monitoring Programme) NAMP?",
			options: [
				"Determining status and trends of ambient air quality",
				"Monitoring biodiversity loss",
				"Measuring groundwater quality",
				"Studying agricultural productivity",
			],
			answer: "Determining status and trends of ambient air quality",
		},
		{
			question: "What meteorological parameters are integrated with air quality monitoring under NAMP?",
			options: [
				"Wind speed, wind direction, relative humidity (RH), and temperature",
				"Ozone levels and atmospheric pressure",
				"Precipitation and solar radiation",
				"UV index and cloud cover",
			],
			answer: "Wind speed, wind direction, relative humidity (RH), and temperature",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following is an outcome of eclipsing in air quality indices?",
			options: [
				"Pollution levels are accurately reported",
				"Air quality is overestimated",
				"Air quality is underestimated",
				"All pollutants are equally represented",
			],
			answer: "Air quality is underestimated",
		},
		{
			question: "If an air pollution index shows ambiguity, how is pollution represented?",
			options: [
				"Accurately and without bias",
				"Underestimated due to eclipsing",
				"Overestimated due to minor deviations in a single pollutant",
				"Not represented at all",
			],
			answer: "Overestimated due to minor deviations in a single pollutant",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following is considered a key component in modeling parameters for air quality?",
			options: [
				"Soil composition",
				"Emission sources",
				"Traffic patterns only",
				"Population density",
			],
			answer: "Emission sources",
		},
	],
	week4: [
		{
			question: "Which of the following formula is given for calculating the mean wind speed at plume height?",
			options: [
				"u(z) = u0 (z0/z)",
				"u(z) = u0 (z0/z)^p",
				"u(z) = u0 (z/z0)",
				"u(z) = u0 (z/z0)^p",
			],
			answer: "u(z) = u0 (z/z0)^p",
		},
		{
			question: "How does the wind angle direction with respect to the receptor affect the total concentration of air pollutants?",
			options: [
				"It increases with an increase in wind angle direction.",
				"It remains constant regardless of wind angle direction.",
				"It decreases as the wind angle direction increases.",
				"It is unaffected by the wind angle direction.",
			],
			answer: "It decreases as the wind angle direction increases.",
		},
		{
			question: "The expression for the determination of concentration (C) of a pollutant using the Gaussian dispersion model for a line source is given as: C = (2q)/(√2π σz u SinΦ) exp (−H^2/2σz^2). What is the standard unit of the (σz) standard deviation in the given equation",
			options: [
				"meter/second (m/s)",
				"gram/second (g/s)",
				"meters (m)",
				"micrograms/cubic meters (μg/m3)",
			],
			answer: "meters (m)",
		},
		{
			question: "The initial spread for the interpretation of the area source is given as",
			options: [
				"σyo = S/1.2",
				"σyo = S/2.2",
				"σyo = S/3.2",
				"σyo = S/4.2",
			],
			answer: "σyo = S/2.2",
		},
		{
			question: "On a highway, a lot of vehicles traveling daily release harmful chemical emissions. Consider the average emission rate from the vehicles of a pollutant P1 as 0.05 g/s. Determine the total chemical concentration of pollutant P1 at a point 600 m downwind from the highway on an overcast day. Let the wind be perpendicular to the highway with a speed of 5 m/s. The number of vehicles per unit length (in m) is 0.18 m.",
			options: [
				"1.44 μg/m3",
				"14.44 μg/m3",
				"2.88 μg/m3",
				"28.8 μg/m3",
			],
			answer: "28.8 μg/m3",
		},
		{
			question: "What does \"assimilative capacity\" of air environment refer to?",
			options: [
				"The amount of pollution that can be discharged without violating water standards",
				"The maximum amount of pollution that can be discharged without violating air quality standards",
				"The ability of air to remain stagnant without pollutants spreading",
				"The rate at which pollutants are produced in an industrial area",
			],
			answer: "The maximum amount of pollution that can be discharged without violating air quality standards",
		},
		{
			question: "What does a higher ventilation coefficient indicate?",
			options: [
				"Poor air quality due to stagnation",
				"Inefficient dispersal of pollutants",
				"Efficient atmospheric dispersion and better air quality",
				"Increased levels of hazardous pollution",
			],
			answer: "Efficient atmospheric dispersion and better air quality",
		},
		{
			question: "The height of the layer in which air pollutants or any constituents emitted or entrained into it is vertically dispersed due to turbulence and convection; it is called",
			options: [
				"Mixing height",
				"Effective height",
				"Plume rise",
				"Ventilation coefficient",
			],
			answer: "Mixing height",
		},
		{
			question: "How is the emission factor (EF) expressed?",
			options: [
				"As the ratio of pollutants to air quality index",
				"As mass of pollutants divided by a volume or weight of raw material",
				"As the proportion of emission to meteorological variations",
				"As the concentration of pollutants in the mixing layer",
			],
			answer: "As mass of pollutants divided by a volume or weight of raw material",
		},
		{
			question: "What does a gridded emission inventory provide?",
			options: [
				"Information on global wind patterns",
				"Locational information of emissions of air pollutants and their sources",
				"Data on rainfall and its effect on pollution",
				"The chemical composition of pollutants in the atmosphere",
			],
			answer: "Locational information of emissions of air pollutants and their sources",
		},
	],
	week5: [
		{
			question: "Which of the following limitations is/are NOT associated with the EMPA model used for estimating vehicular emissions? (i) Inclusion of a catalyst model should lead to improvements in the existing model (ii) It has been developed only for Light Duty Vehicle (iii) Include the dynamic behavior of the engine Select the correct answer",
			options: [
				"(i), (iii)",
				"(ii)",
				"(iii)",
				"(i), (ii) & (iii)",
			],
			answer: "(iii)",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following air pollutants is NOT considered in the VAPI (Vehicular Air Pollution Inventory) model?",
			options: [
				"CO",
				"CO2",
				"PM",
				"O3",
			],
			answer: "O3",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the primary purpose of the MARKAL (MARKet ALlocation) model?",
			options: [
				"To assess the economic growth of developing countries",
				"To model energy systems and compliance with climate change agreements",
				"To monitor air quality and pollution",
				"To optimize agricultural productivity",
			],
			answer: "To model energy systems and compliance with climate change agreements",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the primary focus of the GAINS model?",
			options: [
				"Managing international energy trade agreements",
				"Estimating costs and potentials for air pollution control and GHG mitigation",
				"Monitoring local air quality using satellite imagery",
				"Predicting future changes in rainfall patterns due to pollution",
			],
			answer: "Estimating costs and potentials for air pollution control and GHG mitigation",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following pollutants is primarily emitted from livestock enteric fermentation and rice cultivation?",
			options: [
				"Methane (CH4)",
				"Nitrous oxide (N2O)",
				"Ammonia (NH3)",
				"Fine particulate matter (PM2.5)",
			],
			answer: "Methane (CH4)",
		},
		{
			question: "What source contributes to the release of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) in agriculture?",
			options: [
				"Metabolic processes of vegetation and livestock",
				"Fertilization of soils",
				"Diesel engines in machinery",
				"Both a) and c)",
			],
			answer: "Both a) and c)",
		},
		{
			question: "What activities are covered under the residential sector in relation to fuel combustion?",
			options: [
				"Heating, boiler operation, and commercial cooking",
				"Domestic cooking and use of fireplaces",
				"Captive power generation in offices",
				"Waste management and recycling",
			],
			answer: "Domestic cooking and use of fireplaces",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following facilities are commonly found in urban areas contributing to commercial sector emissions?",
			options: [
				"Hospitals, shopping malls, and crematoriums",
				"Agricultural fields and farmhouses",
				"Rural community centers and livestock farms",
				"Schools and public parks",
			],
			answer: "Hospitals, shopping malls, and crematoriums",
		},
		{
			question: "Which component is used to detect CO, CO2, and HC in transport emission inventory using remote sensing?",
			options: [
				"Twin dispersive ultraviolet (UV) spectrometer",
				"Non-dispersive infrared (NDIR) component",
				"Laser interferometer",
				"Gas chromatography",
			],
			answer: "Non-dispersive infrared (NDIR) component",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the primary purpose of Aerosol Optical Depth (AOD)?",
			options: [
				"To express the quantity of light removed by aerosols in the atmosphere",
				"To measure the concentration of NO2 in urban areas",
				"To determine the source of gaseous emissions",
				"To calculate the pH level of rainwater",
			],
			answer: "To express the quantity of light removed by aerosols in the atmosphere",
		},
	],
	week6: [
		{
			question: "What is EPA's AP-42 (2000) used for emission calculations?",
			options: [
				"Modeling wind speed",
				"Measuring the concentration of gaseous pollutants",
				"Providing emission factors for pollutants not listed elsewhere",
				"Determining the thermal efficiency of fuels",
			],
			answer: "Providing emission factors for pollutants not listed elsewhere",
		},
		{
			question: "Where is a kerb site location typically found?",
			options: [
				"Near a water body",
				"Alongside a pavement",
				"On the outskirts of a city",
				"Far from any pavement",
			],
			answer: "Alongside a pavement",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the primary goal of the bottom-up or source-based method?",
			options: [
				"To ignore emissions sources",
				"To avoid documenting the potential for secondary aerosol formation",
				"To locate pollution sources and develop emission inventories",
				"To avoid chemical transport modeling",
			],
			answer: "To locate pollution sources and develop emission inventories",
		},
		{
			question: "In the mass balance equation, 𝑥𝑖𝑗 = ∑ 𝑔𝑖𝑘𝑓𝑘𝑗𝑝𝑘=1, 𝑥𝑖𝑗 represents:",
			options: [
				"The concentration of the jth species in the ith sample",
				"Source profile for the kth source",
				"The emission factor of a pollutant",
				"The meteorological factor influencing dispersion",
			],
			answer: "The concentration of the jth species in the ith sample",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following pollutants are receptor models mainly used to analyze?",
			options: [
				"Ozone (O3)",
				"Carbon dioxide (CO2)",
				"Particulate matter (PM)",
				"Nitric oxide (NO)",
			],
			answer: "Particulate matter (PM)",
		},
		{
			question: "What visual test is commonly used to assess the normality of data?",
			options: [
				"Normal probability plots",
				"Pie charts",
				"Line graphs",
				"Bar charts",
			],
			answer: "Normal probability plots",
		},
		{
			question: "Which is a common myth about air pollution?",
			options: [
				"Air pollution occurs only outdoors",
				"Air pollution occurs indoors and outdoors equally",
				"Air pollution is harmless",
				"Air pollution is caused by poor air quality only",
			],
			answer: "Air pollution occurs only outdoors",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following is NOT a cause of indoor air pollution?",
			options: [
				"Air tightness of buildings",
				"Poorly designed air conditioning systems",
				"High altitudes",
				"Indoor sources of pollution",
			],
			answer: "High altitudes",
		},
		{
			question: "How does excess oxygen affect the formation of carbon monoxide?",
			options: [
				"It decreases the formation of CO",
				"It increases the formation of CO",
				"It has no effect on CO formation",
				"It makes CO more visible",
			],
			answer: "It decreases the formation of CO",
		},
		{
			question: "Where are levels of lead in soil typically higher?",
			options: [
				"Near schools and playgrounds",
				"Near sources such as lead smelters, mines, and heavily trafficked roadways",
				"In urban parks",
				"Near agricultural fields using organic methods",
			],
			answer: "Near sources such as lead smelters, mines, and heavily trafficked roadways",
		},
	],

	week7: [
		{
			question: "What are the immediate health effects of exposure to indoor air pollutants?",
			options: [
				"Respiratory diseases and cancer",
				"Irritation of eyes, nose, and throat",
				"Cardiovascular diseases",
				"Neurological",
			],
			answer: "Irritation of eyes, nose, and throat",
		},
		{
			question: "Asbestosis, a serious progressive, long-term, non-cancer disease of the lungs is associated with the exposure of:",
			options: [
				"Particulate matter",
				"Second hand smoke",
				"Asbestos",
				"Volatile organics compounds (VOCs)",
			],
			answer: "Asbestos",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the primary goal of exposure assessment for indoor air pollutants?",
			options: [
				"To enhance building aesthetics",
				"To identify pollutant sources and quantify risks",
				"To promote the use of natural ventilation",
				"To calculate construction costs",
			],
			answer: "To identify pollutant sources and quantify risks",
		},
		{
			question: "Which type of sampling relies on the kinetic energy of gas molecules and diffusion of the gases in an enclosed space onto a sorbent medium?",
			options: [
				"Active sampling",
				"Passive sampling",
				"Stratified sampling",
				"Cluster sampling",
			],
			answer: "Passive sampling",
		},
		{
			question: "Which method is commonly used in Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) modelling?",
			options: [
				"Finite element method",
				"Box modelling",
				"Well-mixed model",
				"Stratified sampling",
			],
			answer: "Finite element method",
		},
		{
			question: "Which modelling approach assumes spatially uniform pollutant concentrations indoors?",
			options: [
				"Box model",
				"Well-mixed model",
				"CFD model",
				"Advection model",
			],
			answer: "Well-mixed model",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the primary advantage of using HEPA filters for air cleaning?",
			options: [
				"They remove both gaseous and particulate pollutants.",
				"They are cost-effective for large spaces.",
				"They effectively capture fine and ultrafine particles.",
				"They eliminate microbial contaminants.",
			],
			answer: "They effectively capture fine and ultrafine particles.",
		},
		{
			question: "Which technology is most effective in reducing microbial contamination in indoor air?",
			options: [
				"UVGI systems",
				"Ionizers",
				"Activated carbon filters",
				"Cyclone separators",
			],
			answer: "UVGI systems",
		},
		{
			question: "According to case study \"Personal Exposure to Fine Particles: A Case Study\" which method is used to measure personal exposure to PM2.5?",
			options: [
				"High-volume air sampling",
				"Palm sized optical sensors",
				"Passive diffusion tubes",
				"Infrared imaging",
			],
			answer: "Palm sized optical sensors",
		},
		{
			question: "According to case study \"Personal Exposure to Fine Particles: A Case Study\" which activities had the highest exposure to fine particles?",
			options: [
				"Traffic and cooking",
				"Market",
				"Workplace",
				"Classroom",
			],
			answer: "Traffic and cooking",
		},
	],
	week8: [
		{
			question: "According to case study \"Indoor Air Quality in Nursery Buildings, UAE – Case Study\" What measures were adopted to monitor indoor air quality in nursery buildings in the UAE?",
			options: [
				"Controlling the source of pollutants",
				"Improving ventilation",
				"Removing pollutants via purification",
				"All the above",
			],
			answer: "All the above",
		},
		{
			question: "Controlling the source of pollutants, improving ventilation and removing pollutants via purification.",
			options: [
				"True",
				"False",
			],
			answer: "True",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the primary substance responsible for ozone layer depletion?",
			options: [
				"Methane (CH4)",
				"Chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs)",
				"Carbon Dioxide (CO2)",
				"Ammonia (NH3)",
			],
			answer: "Chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs)",
		},
		{
			question: "Which international treaty was established to address ozone depletion?",
			options: [
				"Kyoto Protocol",
				"Paris Agreement",
				"Montreal Protocol",
				"Basel Convention",
			],
			answer: "Montreal Protocol",
		},
		{
			question: "What is a major cause of global warming?",
			options: [
				"Particulate matter emission",
				"Accumulation of greenhouse gases like CO2 and CH4",
				"Deforestation in tropical regions",
				"Loss of biodiversity",
			],
			answer: "Accumulation of greenhouse gases like CO2 and CH4",
		},
		{
			question: "Which human activity is the largest contributor to methane emissions?",
			options: [
				"Industrial manufacturing",
				"Fossil fuel combustion",
				"Livestock farming and rice cultivation",
				"Urban infrastructure development",
			],
			answer: "Livestock farming and rice cultivation",
		},
		{
			question: "GHGs act like a blanket wrapped around the Earth, trapping the outgoing longwave (infrared) radiation from the earth surface and thus declining global atmospheric temperature.",
			options: [
				"True",
				"False",
			],
			answer: "False",
		},
		{
			question: "Which Sustainable Development Goals (SDG) focuses on action to combat climate change and its impacts?",
			options: [
				"SDG – 6",
				"SDG – 10",
				"SDG – 13",
				"SDG – 16",
			],
			answer: "SDG – 13",
		},
		{
			question: "Which pollutants are responsible for the formation of acid rain?",
			options: [
				"Methane (CH4) and carbon monoxide (CO)",
				"Sulfur dioxide (SO2) and nitrogen oxides (NOx)",
				"Volatile organic compounds (VOCs) and ozone (O3)",
				"Ammonia (NH3) and particulate matter (PM2.5)",
			],
			answer: "Sulfur dioxide (SO2) and nitrogen oxides (NOx)",
		},
		{
			question: "What is a significant effect of acid rain on aquatic ecosystems?",
			options: [
				"Increased water temperatures",
				"Lowering pH levels, leading to the death of aquatic organisms",
				"Increased levels of dissolved oxygen in water",
				"Decreased biodiversity in terrestrial environments",
			],
			answer: "Lowering pH levels, leading to the death of aquatic organisms",
		},
	],
	week9: [
		{
			question: "Which pollutant is most commonly associated with vehicular emissions?",
			options: [
				"Lead",
				"Nitrogen oxides (NOx)",
				"Ozone",
				"Radon",
			],
			answer: "Nitrogen oxides (NOx)",
		},
		{
			question: "Which device is fitted in vehicles to control air pollution from the tailpipe emissions:",
			options: [
				"Electrostatic precipitator",
				"Catalytic converter",
				"Bag filter",
				"Cyclone separator",
			],
			answer: "Catalytic converter",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the primary function of cyclone separators in air pollution control?",
			options: [
				"Capture gaseous pollutants",
				"Remove large particulate matter from emissions",
				"Neutralize sulfur dioxide emissions",
				"Increase air circulation rates",
			],
			answer: "Remove large particulate matter from emissions",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the primary purpose of baghouse filters in industrial settings?",
			options: [
				"Remove gaseous pollutants from emissions",
				"Capture fine particulate matter",
				"Reduce nitrogen oxides (NOx) levels",
				"Increase the velocity of exhaust gases",
			],
			answer: "Capture fine particulate matter",
		},
		{
			question: "Which air pollution control device is best suited for removing fine mist and liquid droplets?",
			options: [
				"Cyclone separator",
				"Wet scrubber",
				"Ionizer",
				"Baghouse filter",
			],
			answer: "Wet scrubber",
		},
		{
			question: "Biofiltration can be classified as a special type of absorption system that uses irreversible processes to control gaseous contaminants.",
			options: [
				"True",
				"False",
			],
			answer: "True",
		},
		{
			question: "The adsorption process is classified as either physical or chemical. The type of force involved in physical adsorption is",
			options: [
				"Chemical interaction",
				"Van der Waal force",
				"Centrifugal force",
				"No force is involved",
			],
			answer: "Van der Waal force",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following technique is adopted when the contaminant concentration is high enough to make a recovery feasible and economical.",
			options: [
				"Biofiltration",
				"Oxidation",
				"Condensation",
				"Absorption",
			],
			answer: "Condensation",
		},
		{
			question: "Which technology is used to control odorous emissions from wastewater treatment plants?",
			options: [
				"Biofilters",
				"Cyclones",
				"Baghouse filters",
				"Catalytic converters",
			],
			answer: "Biofilters",
		},
		{
			question: "Gasoline fumes evaporating from the fuel tank and carburetor are vented directly into the atmosphere. These emissions are significantly reduced by:",
			options: [
				"The air-injection system",
				"Catalytic converter",
				"Positive crankcase ventilation valve",
				"Evaporative control system",
			],
			answer: "Evaporative control system",
		},
	],
	week10: [
		{
			question: "A cyclone has an inlet width of 20 cm and five effective turns (N = 5). The gas temperature is 350⁰K, and the inlet velocity is 10 m/s. The average particle density is 1.5 g/cm³. What is the cut diameter (particle size collected with 50% efficiency)? The viscosity of air at 350⁰K is 0.0748 kg/m-h.",
			options: [
				"6.94 μm",
				"8.33 μm",
				"12.14 μm",
				"15.55 μm",
			],
			answer: "8.33 μm",
		},
		{
			question: "In a bag house filter, the incoming velocity of the gas is 800 m³/min. the filtering velocity is 4 m/min. Each bag is 20 cm wide and 3 m in length. If the spacing between each bag is 30 m and the wall is 30 cm, the number of bags required is________.",
			options: [
				"95",
				"106",
				"144",
				"225",
			],
			answer: "106",
		},
		{
			question: "An electrostatic precipitator, in which the collection plate area is 100 m², gas flow rate is 3 m³/s, and collection efficiency is 99.5%. The migration velocity is______(in m/s):",
			options: [
				"0.16",
				"0.67",
				"1.54",
				"2.15",
			],
			answer: "0.16",
		},
		{
			question: "Single-stage electrostatic precipitator consisting of two sections formed by plates 5.0 m wide and 7.0 m high on 25 cm centers, handling a gas flow of 3 m³/s. Assume that the migration velocity is 12 cm/s. The collection efficiency of a horizontal flow is__________(in %).",
			options: [
				"98.55 %",
				"98.25 %",
				"99.63 %",
				"99.25 %",
			],
			answer: "99.63 %",
		},
		{
			question: "Gravitational settling chamber under the following conditions: I. Air: Horizontal velocity is 1 m/s Temperature is 75⁰C I. Particle: Specific gravity is 1.5 II. Chamber: Length is 10 m and Height is 2 m III. At 75⁰C viscosity of air is 2.1x10⁻⁵ kg/m-s The minimum size of the particle is____________, that will be removed with 100 per cent efficiency.",
			options: [
				"65.28 μm",
				"71.68 μm",
				"83.55 μm",
				"90.67 μm",
			],
			answer: "71.68 μm",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following pollutants is not included in the revised National Ambient Air Quality Standard (NAAQS, 2009):",
			options: [
				"Ozone",
				"Benzene",
				"Arsenic",
				"Cadmium",
			],
			answer: "Cadmium",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the annual permissible limit for PM2.5 in ambient air as per WHO guidelines 2021?",
			options: [
				"5 μg/m³",
				"10 μg/m³",
				"25 μg/m³",
				"50 μg/m³",
			],
			answer: "5 μg/m³",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the primary goal of the National Clean Air Programme (NCAP) in India?",
			options: [
				"To completely eliminate PM emissions by 2025",
				"To achieve a 20–30% reduction in PM2.5 and PM10 levels by 2024",
				"To reduce vehicular emissions in all cities",
				"To promote urbanization in non-attainment areas",
			],
			answer: "To achieve a 20–30% reduction in PM2.5 and PM10 levels by 2024",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the focus of the Graded Response Action Plan (GRAP)?",
			options: [
				"Managing waste in urban areas",
				"Reducing air pollution during severe episodes in Delhi NCR",
				"Expanding public transportation networks",
				"Implementing electric vehicle subsidies",
			],
			answer: "Reducing air pollution during severe episodes in Delhi NCR",
		},
		{
			question: "Which Indian policy promotes the adoption of electric vehicles to reduce vehicular emissions?",
			options: [
				"National Electric Mobility Mission Plan (NEMMP)",
				"Make in India Program",
				"National Renewable Energy Policy",
				"National Highway Development Project",
			],
			answer: "National Electric Mobility Mission Plan (NEMMP)",
		},
	],
	week11: [
		{
			question: "In 1991, which of the following protocols was related to the control of emissions of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) or their transboundary fluxes?",
			options: [
				"Geneva protocol",
				"Gothenburg Protocol",
				"Stockholm Convention",
				"Helsinki Protocol",
			],
			answer: "Geneva protocol",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the primary goal of the Paris Agreement under the UNFCCC?",
			options: [
				"To phase out ozone-depleting substances",
				"To limit global temperature rise to well below 2°C above pre-industrial levels",
				"To monitor and control air pollution in urban areas",
				"To eliminate greenhouse gas emissions entirely by 2030",
			],
			answer: "To limit global temperature rise to well below 2°C above pre-industrial levels",
		},
		{
			question: "Which treaty focuses on reducing ozone-depleting substances?",
			options: [
				"Kyoto Protocol",
				"Gothenburg Protocol",
				"Montreal Protocol",
				"Stockholm Convention",
			],
			answer: "Montreal Protocol",
		},
		{
			question: "What was an unintended consequence of improved air quality during lockdowns?",
			options: [
				"Decrease in ozone levels in some regions",
				"Increased indoor air pollution",
				"Reduced visibility in urban areas",
				"A slight increase in ground-level ozone in certain cities",
			],
			answer: "A slight increase in ground-level ozone in certain cities",
		},
		{
			question: "To control the dust pollution at the construction site, which one of the mitigation measures would be most effective.",
			options: [
				"Fogging system",
				"Ban on refuse burning",
				"Vehicle usage controls",
				"Bike parking facilities",
			],
			answer: "Fogging system",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following mitigation strategies is focused to reduce the emissions from enhanced the use of clean fuel in rural and urban areas?",
			options: [
				"Congestion pricing",
				"Non-motorised transportation",
				"Pradhan Mantri Ujjwala Yojana",
				"Auto Fuel Policy",
			],
			answer: "Pradhan Mantri Ujjwala Yojana",
		},
		{
			question: "Blending of_______ methanol in gasoline can bring down GHG emissions by 20% in terms of particulate matter, NOx, and SOx, thereby improving the urban air quality.",
			options: [
				"10%",
				"15%",
				"20%",
				"25%",
			],
			answer: "15%",
		},
		{
			question: "What is a finely divided, carbon-rich, porous substance that can be obtained from the crop stubble through the process of Pyrolysis.",
			options: [
				"Composting",
				"Biochar",
				"Mechanical processing",
				"Happy seeder",
			],
			answer: "Biochar",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the size range of PM10 particles?",
			options: [
				"Greater than 10 microns",
				"Less than 10 microns in diameter",
				"Between 10 and 50 microns",
				"Exactly 10 microns",
			],
			answer: "Less than 10 microns in diameter",
		},
		{
			question: "What is the 24 hour National Ambient Air Quality Standard (NAAQS) of PM10 for the residential area (in μg/m³) ?",
			options: [
				"40",
				"60",
				"80",
				"100",
			],
			answer: "100",
		},
	],
	week12: [
		{
			question: "The filter paper used during the sampling of PM2.5 in the ambient air is known as PTFE filter paper, where PTFE refers to",
			options: [
				"Poly tetra fluoro ethylamine",
				"Poly tetra fluoro ethyl",
				"Poly tetra fluoro ethylene",
				"Poly tetra fluoro ethanol",
			],
			answer: "Poly tetra fluoro ethylene",
		},
		{
			question: "According to National Ambient Air Quality Standards (NAAQS), what is the permissible value of 24 hour-concentration of PM2.5 in Ecologically Sensitive Area (Notified by Central Government)",
			options: [
				"40 μg/m³",
				"60 μg/m³",
				"80 μg/m³",
				"100 μg/m³",
			],
			answer: "60 μg/m³",
		},
		{
			question: "The absorbing reagent Potassium Tetrachloro mercurate (TCM) is used in sampling and analysis of:",
			options: [
				"SO₂",
				"NO₂",
				"CO",
				"O₃",
			],
			answer: "SO₂",
		},
		{
			question: "Modified Jacob & Hochheiser Method is used for sampling and analysis of:",
			options: [
				"CO",
				"O₃",
				"SO₂",
				"NO₂",
			],
			answer: "NO₂",
		},
		{
			question: "In which type of sampling the velocity and the direction of the gas entering the sampling nozzle is the same as that of the gas in the duct/stack at the same sampling point.",
			options: [
				"Isothermal sampling",
				"Isokinetic sampling",
				"Adiabatic sampling",
				"Differential sampling",
			],
			answer: "Isokinetic sampling",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following method is used to measure sulphur dioxide SO2 from the gas sample extracted from the sampling point of the stack.",
			options: [
				"Barium thorin titration method",
				"Improved West and Gaeke method",
				"Modified Jacob and Hochheiser method",
				"Gravimetric method",
			],
			answer: "Barium thorin titration method",
		},
		{
			question: "Which pollutants are typically monitored using multi-gas monitors?",
			options: [
				"CO, CO2, VOCs, and ozone",
				"PM2.5 and PM10",
				"Heavy metals and ammonia",
				"Sulfur dioxide and nitrogen dioxide",
			],
			answer: "CO, CO2, VOCs, and ozone",
		},
		{
			question: "Which of the following parameters is measured using the non-dispersive infrared spectroscopy in multi gas monitor.",
			options: [
				"Temperature",
				"Percent Relative Humidity (%RH)",
				"Carbon Monoxide (CO)",
				"Carbon Dioxide (CO2)",
			],
			answer: "Carbon Dioxide (CO2)",
		},
		{
			question: "What principle is commonly used in spectrometers to analyze particulate matter?",
			options: [
				"Light scattering and laser diffraction",
				"Mass spectrometry",
				"Gravimetric analysis",
				"Infrared absorption",
			],
			answer: "Light scattering and laser diffraction",
		},
		{
			question: "The minimum time interval for monitoring of the particulate matter using the spectrometer software is:",
			options: [
				"45 seconds",
				"30 seconds",
				"12 seconds",
				"6 seconds",
			],
			answer: "6 seconds",
		},
	],
};